Guide to the Political Science Department Records 1950-1967
Oregon State University Libraries, University Archives
Political Science Department Records
1950-1967
1950-1964
Oregon State University Libraries, Special Collections & Archives Research Center University Archives 121 The Valley Library Oregon State University Corvallis, OR 97331-4501 Phone: 541-737-2165 Email: archives@oregonstate.edu Web: http://osulibrary.oregonstate.edu/archives
RG 075
Oregon State University. Dept. of Political Science.
0.1 cubic foot, including 33 photographs 2 boxes
The Political Science Department Records consist primarily of materials documenting the annual Institute on World Affairs held at Oregon State College in the 1950s. Political science courses have been taught at Oregon State since the 1860s.
Historical Note:
Courses in political science, political economy, and government have been taught at Oregon State University since its founding in the 1860s. In 1908, political science courses were taught within the School of Commerce and a Department of Political Science was established within the School of Commerce in the 1910s. In the early 1930s, with the establishment of the Oregon State System of Higher Education, political science became a unit of the Lower Division and offered a limited number of courses. Political science at Oregon State expanded significantly during the 1950s and several faculty were hired. The School of Humanities and Social Sciences was established in 1959 with the Political Science Department as one of its units. An undergraduate degree in political science was first offered in 1966.
The Institute on World Affairs was held annually at Oregon State College from 1950 through 1959. The event was sponsored by Oregon State College, Corvallis community groups, and the Oregon Commission for UNESCO and included convocations, lectures, and discussion groups.
The Model United Nations is an academic simulation of the United Nations with the purpose of educating participants about current events, diplomacy, and communication. Oregon State University students participated in Model United Nations conferences in the 1950s through 1970s.
The Political Science Department Records consist primarily of records and photographs of the Institute on World Affairs held at Oregon State College in the 1950s. Brochures for several symposia on world affairs held in the 1960s are also included. Photographs of participants and activities in the 1964 Model United Nations are part of the collection.
All photographs are b/w prints.
Collection is open for research.
The records are arranged in two series: I. Institute on World Affairs, 1950-1967 and II. Model United Nations Photographs, 1964.
The materials were acquired by the Archives in two accessions in 1986 and 1991.
Additions to the collection are expected.
The Memorabilia Collection includes additional information about the Political Science Departments academic programs and faculty as well as the Model United Nations. The College of Liberal Arts Records (RG 143) document academic programs in humanities and social sciences at Oregon State and include the records of several other social science departments including anthropology, economics, history and sociology. The Archives collections also include Studies in Political Science (PUB 5-34i) published by the OSU Press. Additional photographs of the Model United Nations are part of the Gwil Evans Photographic collection (P 082).
Oregon State University--Students.; United Nations--Study and teaching.; Oregon State College. Institute on World Affairs.
College students--Oregon--Corvallis.; International relations--Congresses.; Student activities--Oregon--Corvallis.
Photographic prints.
Colleges and Universities; International Relations; Student Life; Oregon; Corvallis; Photographs
- Institute on World Affairs, 1950-1967; Series I
  Series I consists primarily of paper records and photographs of the Institute on World Affairs held at Oregon State College in the 1950s. Several of the institutes focused on Asia, including Korea and Southeast Asia; others addressed issues in Africa and the Soviet Union. The records include brochures, programs, newspaper clippings, correspondence, and the text of speeches. The photographs are of institute speakers and participants. The paper records also include brochures for several symposia on world affairs held at Oregon State University in the 1960s.
  - Paper Records, 1950-1967 (Box 1)
  - Photographs, 1952-1953
    - Dr. Franz Michael and Dr. S.Y. Wu, 1952; P197:19 (Box 2)
    - Dr. Claude A. Buss, 1953; P197:20; 2 prints (Box 2)
    - Unidentified Institute participants, 1953; P197:21 - P197:24; 6 prints (Box 2)
- Model United Nations Photographs, 1964; Series II; 24 prints
  Series II consists of photographs depicting activities and participants at the 1964 Model United Nations.
  - Delegates at work, P197:01 (Box 2)
  - The International Court of Justice hearing a charge against Turkey by Greece, P197:02; 2 prints (Box 2)
  - Steve Hutchinson (center) of the University of Oregon chats with Gil Tolin (right) of Oregon State University during a session at the Rules Committee, P197:03; 2 prints (Box 2)
  - Delegates at work, P197:04 - P197:05 (Box 2)
  - Delegates at work at round tables, P197:06; 2 prints (Box 2)
  - OSU delegation, representing China, listens to debate during a plenary meeting of the General Assembly, P197:07; 2 prints (Box 2)
  - Unidentified speaker, P197:08 (Box 2)
  - Exterior of building (not at Oregon State University), P197:09 (Box 2)
  - Margot Ezekiel votes for China during a regular meeting of the Economic and Social Council, P197:10; 2 prints (Box 2)
  - Delegates for Bolivia and China, P197:11 (Box 2)
  - Barbara Land pauses during session of the Economic and Financial Committee, P197:12 (Box 2)
  - Unidentified work session, P197:13 - P197:14 (Box 2)
  - General assembly in a large coliseum, P197:15 (Box 2)
  - Unidentified delegate, P197:16; 2 prints (Box 2)
  - Unidentified speaker, P197:17 (Box 2)
  - Delegates in auditorium, P197:18 (Box 2)